[Music]
hello and welcome everyone it's june
15th 2022 and we're here in actinflob
live stream number 46.1
welcome up and mute the stream if you
have in the
background thank you
welcome to the active inference lab
we are a participatory online lab that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at some of the links on the slide
this is a recorded and an archived
and transcribed and edited and published
live stream
so please provide feedback so we can
improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
live streams and a lot of the other
projects that are happening
in the lab
so we're here in acting stream 46.1
and we're in our second discussion of
the paper active inference models do not
contradict folk psychology
by ryan smith maxwell ramstad and alex
kiefer and
we're gonna go
i expect in many fun and interesting
directions today
so thanks everybody who's joined the
panel live and also for those who are
watching live thanks for adding your
comments in the live chat
we'll begin with some introductions
and then i believe that will introduce
many interesting areas we can continue
from there
so
we can start by just introducing ourself
and then passing it to someone else who
has not yet spoken and will close with
the authors who are here
so i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and the dot zero was very interesting
with jacob and dean and ryan and it
raised many questions that i was excited
to discuss today
just to provide one would be perhaps the
relationship between formalisms of any
kind
and
natural language and just regular
concepts that people have how do we draw
the connection or evaluate connections
that are drawn there
and i'll pass to ali
questions i'd like to ask if they're not
what
oh sorry ellie wait wait uh sorry just
the uh
audio is set up a little bit differently
so if you could
um just start you can just reintroduce
but go for it thank you
uh okay is it okay yes yes
thank you all right
yeah uh i'm an independent researcher
from iran
and uh as i said i also have a couple of
questions i'd like to ask um if they're
not addressed during the discussion
especially when we get to section nine
of the paper
and
yeah i'm very glad to be here and
that's it from me and i'll pass it to
dean
morning uh my name is dean
i'm uh here in calgary
uh
i
really like this
paper which i kind of indicated in the
last
last live stream my
my curiosity because i really don't know
is
because of my background in education um
when i'm looking at that sort of
qualification quantification
piece and i'm thinking about the desires
as something that we can
see as 0.1 and 0.9 as a distribution i
often thought of
some of my previous conversations around
things like likert scales and so
i know this people haven't addressed
those things specifically but the idea
of being able to
translate into
sort of a numeric form has always been
interesting to me and that's something
that maybe
today or maybe in the 0.2 we can
we can think about the implications of
that and i'll pass it to
david
hey david kelton here uh thanks for
having me on my first time here on
active infant inference i go
by duvet as a streamer
i'm a civil engineer by uh education and
practice my background linguistics and
uh
physics and psychology
i spent many years in yeshiva rabbinic
study and i've been practicing hindu i'm
more on the mystical side of
consciousness been studying it actively
streaming for
a few years but also the mathematical
uh
materialistic side so yeah this paper
was very interesting especially you know
dealing with the sense perception
related to motor control which uh you
know my perception of dualism is
something that
the material does actually control so i
like the model i like the paper i was
interested in looking at some of the
more
um
philosophical and even
mystical precursors what what could
actually be explained
what are the assumptions being uh being
made in this paper was definitely a good
start
thank you david and to alex so feel free
to give any introduction and then
provide any context on what brought
about the paper from your perspective
yeah thanks uh so i'm alex kiefer i'm
i'm one of the authors on the paper uh
i'm uh affiliated with with um
monash university and and jakob obi's
cognition philosophy lab there and uh
i currently um
also uh
my my main sort of gig is at uh versus
uh research labs uh in la so
uh we've been doing some really
interesting research there that plugs
into active inference among other things
um
so as far as uh
context for the paper
um
so this is uh this issue of how how and
whether active inference and
and and theories in the vicinity like
predictive processing uh and all that uh
how those things map onto folk
psychology it's something i've been
interested in for a long time uh before
i uh i
spoke to ryan and maxwell that's about
this paper
uh and um
i won't try to give ryan's uh side of
the of the backstory but basically he he
was
i think planning on drafting something
along these lines for
independently uh we got in touch
um
through carl first and i think and uh
uh you know it was pointed out that i
was drafting something on the same thing
uh and then i ended up just hopping on
board
to work on certain sections and to sort
of to sort of uh help carry through the
argument
so that's a little bit of background
awesome what sections we can look at the
road map
did you um work on or also if you have
any thoughts on this overall structure
of like what sections did you include
and why did you order them in that way
yeah i mean i i guess i mean really we
share credit for it for all of it like
it's there isn't anything you know i i
um
we contributed to the
to the whole paper um
but the the sections that i was more
that i leaned more on maybe and that i
contributed more to
uh were the thing about
uh quantifying the motivational force of
desires um
section seven and then we also had a
bunch of back and forth um about the
last few sections the free energy
principle and direction of fit
um
yeah so i mean ryan being the first
author
definitely definitely did um a lot of
the writing so but those are the
sections that i had more more to do with
directly
awesome and then just one more question
alex so that we can go back to our open
uh
list of topics
what would you characterize the big
question of the paper as what do you
think would bring somebody to this paper
because they were wondering x
yeah i mean so it's pretty i think it's
pretty clear in this in this case right
fortunately it's pretty easy it's just
the question is whether
uh
the active inference formalism uh
particularly a certain strain of that
that the sort of the street decision
uh decision
um model
uh flavor of active inference is
is consistent with or compatible with
um
folk psychology and the bdi model in
particular
great okay and then also what would you
characterize the bdi model as
and then we'll um open up for more
questions but just to get some of the
prerequisites and you're right that it
is um great that it is clear many papers
have much more esoteric big questions
and this one is very like down the
middle
yeah yeah one thing i liked about about
working with
with ryan is that he
he sort of wanted to just make the title
of a paper a declarative like sentence
that says
this is what we're claiming and i really
like that i'm going to try to follow
that so my own
work
um but the bdi model um i don't think i
have a whole lot to add here either it's
just the
idea fundamentally that beliefs and
desires interact to form intentions
and that that's uh
i would i guess maybe also that
that that's a legitimate way to explain
behavior
for some class of
systems intelligence systems people
agents
all right
awesome so
ali dean or duvet if you have any
uh questions you'd like to raise at this
time otherwise we'll go into one of
these
pieces we've raced yes stupid
it just uh i'd never heard of hilton or
the folk psychology
bdm model
um
is that
a prominent model you purposely chose or
could
this be uh
you'll fill in for basically any
non-scientific or introspective
or even duelist uh
model for uh
for consciousness or is it specific this
hilton
uh
model and
are you claiming that it fails
as a materialistic uh
model
um
yeah so i think i think part of the
reason we referred to the bdi model was
to just be
to sort of bracket for the purposes of
the paper although i'm happy to discuss
it here um
a lot of questions that might arise
about vocal psychology and what exactly
is meant by that so if we just say we're
talking about
the idea that beliefs and desires
interact to form intentions
then
that's a clear target and then of course
there are many different
conceptions of uh many maybe there are
many different folk psychologies and and
and um
views on
uh in that vicinity but like
uh i guess yeah the vdi uh
models is sort of maybe
supposed to be like an essence that you
can distill from many of those different
perspectives now maybe that's not true
we can talk about whether the bdi model
is really common to
different conceptions of folk psychology
because i i you know
i have to think about that i i kind of i
kind of assume that it is um i'm curious
about the the materialism dualism issue
i don't see
i guess directly how it plays into
things at this level of description
because um
i guess we're not claiming necessarily
that beliefs and desires are material or
not
uh
at this stage but anyway i'm happy to
get into that
yeah feel free to unpack that david
yeah i mean just classically uh you know
obviously people have had minds for
you know as long as human existence you
know maybe if you believe in julian
james and evolution
that there was an origin to a
consciousness in the mind
at some point but you know historically
uh
most of the western tradition up to a
few hundred years ago believe that these
things originated
from a non-material source you know
whether it's your soul however you want
to explain it
but you know is the controller from the
a greek model of the soul uh ethos uh
logos pathos or
um and any model
that you know so beliefs and desires
that that would be the controller
that would
be decisive in these uh cognitive
functions don't arise from the material
so if you have a materialistic model
where you're saying that these things do
in fact arise from the brain
you could say that uh you know the
ancients were just incorrect
either either in ascribing
non-material origins to things that have
material origins
or you could say they were completely
incorrect and like in a limited
perspective that there is no such thing
as belief or desire or there is no such
thing as a as like a unified
um eye so if you meant hilton has some
sort of material
division even freud like even even going
back to freud just 100 years ago
the question of the psyche and the
subconscious
you know whether that has material
origins or not is unclear
right
yeah so so i guess i guess my
perspective on this i'm sort of a
methodological materialist about these
things like
i think that you can
uh
insofar as so in terms like the scope of
this of this kind of explanation that we
discussed in this paper
and
active inference in general um
works with i think i think
any anything that you can explain about
the causes of of intelligent behavior
i think you can probably put a material
uh
gloss on that but i i'm not personally
i'm not really committed to the claim
that you can explain everything about
people
uh in terms of input output mappings you
know but but insofar as you can conceive
of some function whether cognition
perception whatever as a sort of input
output mapping in space of behavior then
i think you can explain it using
these frameworks interpreted as
descriptions of brain processes um
so it's interesting that you kind of
contrast
or you suggest that maybe there's an
argument for eliminativism
if
if you were thinking of
mental states as
having us a root or a source in
something non-material maybe then if you
reject that idea then you'd be prone to
limit eliminativism but um
so i'm very much
so coming back to the idea i'm i'm
starting from a sort of methodological
materialist standpoint but i'm
definitely not limited to this i
actually
the one thing i wanted to get into today
is i really don't understand
um
i don't understand
how eliminativism is a tenable position
with respect to folk psychology if
you're a materialist
um because i think that there's just
well i will i'll hold off on getting
into that but um
i think i guess i'll just just one last
comment on this i think the question of
whether beliefs and desires and
intentions and other mental states have
any non-material aspect and the question
of whether they exist and whether they
should be eliminated from ontology are
distinct
thank you i think this is a fine place
we'll have a lot of time to explore
other avenues but it would be awesome if
you could describe the limitivism
and also
um there was a quote in your paper where
it says
if the worry is founded that there's a
tension between active inference and
folk psychology specifically the bdi
model
it could be taken either to imply that
active inference models are implausible
because reasons
or
if and to the extent that the models are
successful to imply that desires should
be eliminated from scientific theories
of psychology so what is a limitivism
and how did you
interact with that topic
right so so eliminativism is uh as we're
using it here is and i think this is the
mainstream stance
is
is just the view well i guess okay the
most general version of the view with
respect to anything is just that
that that thing should be sort of
eliminated from serious discourse or
serious theory uh maybe scientific
theory
um
and i mean the
the
the idea that the church ones have in
defending elimination about
folk psychology is that it's it's like a
failed theory so basically the idea is
if you know theories i suppose um
survive on the basis of their predictive
and explanatory power
and
some other criteria you know theoretical
virtues the ability to evolve and
explain new anomalies apparent anomalies
that crop up so the churchlings
basically
think that uh full psychology has failed
this test
uh so the theory of folk psychology has
been falsified that we should just move
on
and that's
that's i i would say
you know to be sort of uh
precise that's that's a version of
eliminativism applied to
mental states um but that's the view
that we're really talking about here
okay yes david please
yeah i guess there i mean there's
different schools in in elimination but
uh if you want to take that to
consciousness studies in totality
or questions of free will or you know i
can mention the ancient dualistic
understanding of uh
consciousness
is you could take elimination to
consciousness in totality that the the
man is a mechanistic
computer and even
you know as a mystic i would argue
possibly against the strong
interpretation of active inference
that's a
atheistic elimination model and you
might
not you know for philosophical reasons
not want to be eliminativists
and therefore try to defend it uh but uh
then you know what are the mathematics
what are your claims
actually say uh but yeah i mean the
strong levels say that uh there is no
uh there is no belief there is no desire
there is no unified eye
and we're just a automaton that uh
uh has some sort of threshold
interaction
with the environment
and whatever
perception are ahead
that you know we have voices in our head
that might make us think that we're
conscious beings might make us think
that we have self-control
or you know beliefs or even free will
are essentially illusions of the mind
that have nothing to do uh with our
actions
i could just
how do i do follow-up
authors
well
great um
yeah i would just it's a good question
how consciousness fits into this picture
and i i'm not sure whether whether the
version of eliminativism that i took
myself to be targeting here includes
consciousness or not it's mostly been a
view that's focused on the idea of
discrete mental states that play these
functional roles beliefs and desires and
so forth
so um yeah i definitely think there's
further questions about that um
and i can see
yeah i can see how you might interpret
active inference not just active
inference but almost any mainstream sort
of
um
you know theory and like neuro
psychology and that vein as as
implying a form of eliminativism if you
think that these mental states aren't
are
by definition
um not
material or not entirely material but
again i'm happy to get into that further
yes um
the uh
the idea that
any kind of modeling
by making it specific
is approaching or on the road or
slippery slope or already reached the
point of eliminating the need for
appeals outside of that description it's
also possible to consider that an entire
category error and say
we're describing
brain processes which is i believe what
you said earlier and no description of a
sunset
is the territory of the sunset math is
not the territory as we hear
often
and so how can one be eliminativist
about
a process
with any kind of description
whether it's predictive processing or
active inference or
any other kind of
model
um
yeah i raised my raise my hand here um
i'll just raise my actual hand um
yeah i mean another thing i
consistently just said that i should
bring up here is that uh
i mean strictly speaking i suppose
active inference isn't committed to
these being
directly descriptions of brain processes
they're right they're sort of
computational models of decision-making
processes with beliefs and all that and
of course if you take the there's this
whole background of the free energy
principle and all that that links this
to physics and the physic the physical
nature of systems uh and i tend to read
these models as pretty transparently
mapping onto brain processes but
it's not
necessarily the case that that you need
to be committed to that interpretation
of these processes as material processes
when you use active inference
to describe some system at the
psychological level
and there's of course still a lot of
question about how the psychological
description maps on to the physical
description which i have views about but
it's an open question
awesome uh dean and then ali
so in the paper itself on page seven i
think there's a paragraph that kind of
refers to all of this that we've been
talking about i'll just quote it the
relationship between conscious and
unconscious
computation
therefore remains an open question
that said some specific dai models have
been used to describe higher level
cognitive processes that can generate
conscious beliefs and verbal reports and
then it says who the authors are in
these cases the inferential prediction
error minimization process
can still be seen as subpersonal or
unconscious but the resulting beliefs
and decisions themselves are assumed to
enter awareness
as a general rule however some personal
processes
in dai should not be expected to map
one-to-one with consciously accessible
or personal level processes
great so i've i've copied that up on the
slides and dean what do you think that
spoke to or what made you want to share
that
i just think i think i think the first
author and the and the other authors
were essentially saying
let's make sure that we don't
try to conflate things here that we we
focus in on what we're trying to do here
which is point to
the potential of
these formalisms
explaining something if a person can
self-report if they can't there's still
aspects of this that might apply but i
think i think they were just trying to
clarify exactly what they were pointing
to and not
pointing to
and ryan smith
has made
clearly a line of research as well as
multiple
live streams and exhortations on social
media about this distinction that one
can take a cognitive modeling approach
of report behavior
did you see that or not
and that can be very clearly although
subtly distinguished from the actual
awareness of seeing something it's not
the same thing to have report
um behavior as it is to have the
experiential underpinning
they're
potentially adjacent to questions or
there's a space that they're linked in a
meaningful way but it's quite possible
to blanket
literally
one's uncertainty
about the question of experience even in
a visual or multimodal way
from the question of well let's just say
we had
the
animal
or the computer program in the chair
and now we're making a cognitive model
of its report behavior
different question than can the report
behavior model be one of the same
as what is actually happening because
there could be an inter leaving stage
where they just choose to lie or other
all these other kinds of interesting
things happening
ali
uh yeah and just as a brief side note i
think uh the the term poke psychology
here can also be related to uh the
distinction made by uh wilfred sellers
between manifest image and the
scientific image of human beings and the
manifest image being our understanding
of ourselves are as personal and social
beings and obviously the scientific
image speaks for self so i think the
term folk psychology
can possibly be
equivalent to
this manifest image of ourselves and um
yeah
that's just a side note
i wanted to share
how do you see that alex
yeah i think i mean i i'd almost agree i
would just say maybe
i don't i don't think i would say full
psychology is equivalent to the manifest
image but i think it might be a part of
it which is probably nitpicking but
there just might be more to the manifest
image of ourselves than just
psychology but
anyway i basically agree
yes the the question yeah dean anything
you want to
bring here
no
this reminds me of with
the conversations we've had on
linguistics how there's one view on
language
as a entity like out there body of
knowledge and then there's also the
person's
self-constructed
sense of
language
and they only have a partial subset of
the words or they use them in a certain
way
and there's an analogous
distinction where
there's folk psychology
the academic field of
versus people's inner sense and how do
people generate their inner sense of
manifest image if if that's appropriate
and how can that be
connected and mapped to
again any descriptive model or
disciplinary or transdisciplinary model
on alex and then do it
yeah so so i really should take the
opportunity to say that my my conception
of how folk psychology works is like
thoroughly sellers celerzian it's like
i think he got exactly right so
basically and it's been a long time
since i've tried to recite this but
basically just
um
the idea that there's sort of uh
verbal behavior right that people enact
and engage engage in
that we end up sort of associating with
um other things that are going on
internally and that
through this sort of uh process we end
up sort of inadvertently in the course
of evolutionary history at some point
there's this whole
uh silasian myth about this stuff but
basically
the idea is that folk psychology sort of
arises and introspection things like
that um
and i may be putting a bit more into
sellers than he actually says right now
again it's been a while but basically
the idea that introspection and our
sense of self-awareness and stuff like
that uh sort of
could have developed out of first
um outward behavior
right and then we sort of
become sensitive to correlations among
these outward signals and that develops
sort of an inner sense uh in that way so
um but the idea that the fundamental
idea that's relevant to this discussion
this paper i think is that folk
psychology
is just the name for this this sort of
thing that
naturally developed in the course of
human history i gotta say of course
there isn't just one folk psychology
right there um for one thing people
speak different languages but i do think
the the piece of it that i think is is
pretty
pretty safe to say is true or i i think
and that we meant to capture
this was my take on why we were using
the bdi model is that
i mean pretty much anyone uh this isn't
entirely true there are different you
know um dialects and things but
basically
if you want to understand why somebody
did something you can say oh they
believed x and they wanted y
right and they intended
z
and uh that that's the level at which i
i mean to um
sort of endorse full psychology is just
i don't see how
that sort of psychological
and i gotta say it's not for me my
motivation
for
sort of wanting to defense defensively
psychology isn't really anything to do
with
introspection or consciousness it's just
we obviously use these these terms to
explain behavior and we do it very
successfully and so i don't i don't
think it could be the case that these
terms fail to carry information about
the states that people are in
so
you know uh
i don't this is why i don't quite get
the limit to this argument
um
anyway that's gone a bit far our field
before we started
david and then anyone else
um
yeah well i think i mean
as a
say a spiritualist the limiting argument
is saying that's the natural conclusion
of what you're saying in your drawing
from the dualistic tradition
when you use these terminologies so you
know say that all of the thousands of
years of western tradition that believed
in
the soul and then you want to borrow the
terminology from a materialistic point
of view it may not be uh
be accurate and follow the evidence and
think uh you know jerry fodor
and the modular mind or benjamin
liebet's experiments
that uh you know what is active
inference actually saying it's a
threshold
that is reached
that uh causes activity in you know like
leave its famous experiments where uh uh
the threshold is reached and it could be
measured in the brain
before the
you'll call the active conscious part of
the person recognizes it and if it was
like a modular mind uh
that you have multiple conflicting
uh
parts of the person that could have
beliefs and motivation but what we would
call
the you know the module of the mind that
creates the narrative for us is only one
of those and that's just what active to
the person so when i interact with
myself or you interact with another
person through language you only have
access to that one part of the brain
that creates a narrative but you know
said the leave it's experiments
uh
and you know a few a few you know more
recent experience has demonstrated that
uh that's not likely the part that
controls action
and uh your active inference didn't
exist then i mean bayesian mechanics did
but you're saying it's it's a threshold
and there's all sorts
of uh things that cause a person's
threshold to be reached
and uh active inference could
potentially
uh model that and then if you you know
even you put in your paper that you
could include things like
you know if you want to call beliefs or
desires as higher order rules so even at
the point there may not be a mechanistic
understanding of what's the origin or
how these higher order rules operate but
it would be some sort of uh
um your free energy principle some sort
of uh mathematical reduction of a
threshold being reached
where the sum totality of the conscious
and subconscious factors
cause the action and even the person
ourselves through introspection isn't
gonna have full access to that
um
if i can just respond here um
i think first of all just to be
respectful to my co-authors i should say
because i might get into my own views
here which they don't necessarily share
that's all but um i should say i think
this paper is really targeted at
explaining
the connections potentially
or clarifying the connections between
folk psychology
i think
whatever it's whatever its implications
right even whether whether folk
psychology
carries implications of soul type
things because of its roots maybe it
does but anyway it's it's trying to
clarify the connections between
active inference as just as sort of a
formal theory of decision making and
folk psychology
um
i don't
uh so anyway it's it's neutral
technically on the issue of whether
active inference is
true
or is an exhaustive exhaustive or true
description of
what we are and what we do
um
now maybe there's still an issue there
if you really think that folks
psychology
that the terms very terms of folk
psychology carry dualistic implications
and if you and if you think that active
inference
carries materialistic implications then
there's still a problem i guess
um i guess i'm
i don't i don't really know if i if i
agree with either of those but um
yeah i mean i i
i don't i guess i don't see how
um
the
i don't see how active inference as such
implies anything one way or the other
the other about
whether there are
um
non-material
origins to
to behavior
um
it's it
i guess okay i i can see let me try this
see if i can i'm just trying to see if i
get your argument david so it's like
we're saying that active inference or
let's say active inference as a
framework says that this is how
decisions happen you do a
search over policies which are these
discrete
things and you figure out the expected
free energy which has to do with
comparing
sensory data to expected sensory data
and i guess if you think you think all
of those
components are
pieces of a material thing right
they're all beliefs or desires or
something like that
which you take to be
i mean
actually i think i can answer sorry i
realize i'm this i'm not doing the best
job of this right now but at least i'm
getting this is difficult it's i'm glad
you're bringing this stuff up because
this is actually this gets quite
challenging um but i think uh
so so active inference is this theory of
of um well dai is this theory of of
discrete decision making
that appeals to this
you know to these
um
distributions or things that are like
belief distribution of distributions
right a belief distribution and a desire
or a preference distribution
um
i don't think it says anything about
where the preference distribution comes
from and in particular i don't think it
says
um
that it doesn't come from the soul or
you know or some
some deeper thing so that's that
switched from me trying to
rationally reconstruct your argument to
me trying to rebut it sorry about that
but i'm just trying to make some
progress
let me try to walk through some of these
steps because i agree it's an important
distinction so
the focus of the paper the regime of
attention of the paper very clearly
written to remain on a line because
there's many open threads related to for
example different cultural folk
psychologies various folk psychology
models
various metaphysical claims the paper
was focused on identifying
one possible area of incompatibility
which would be the relationship between
the bdi model
entities the nodes in the bdi graph
and
assignments of terms for specific
parts of the active formalism
and identifying that will come back too
now then
as what has been pointed out today
one could ask
if folk psychology carries
a duelist
implication
in the sense of there being material and
non-material types of things
whether implicitly
or axiomatically or historically but if
folk psychology has a dualist
implication
and
active inference carries a purely
materialist implication
implicitly or explicitly then there
could be another
like battlefront
of tension
which would not be based around mapping
the nodes in the bdi model to the nodes
or the formalisms in the actin formalism
which is like a theory theory ontology
map question but this would actually be
a metaphysical
incompatibility and then
alex you walked through some steps that
said if active inference is a framework
that says
this is going to be a model of how
decisions happen
there's a search over discrete policies
there's the calculation of variational
free energy and or expected free energy
and then you added as part of a material
thing
then
it is going to be incompatible with
anything in material
however one could also simply say active
is a descriptive framework saying here's
how i will model how decisions happen
as a search over discrete policies and
as the calculation of fe
then there might be one two three four
kinds of things in the universe
or it could be anything
but this is where the materialism enters
is actually as a clause
in the assumptions
of that string
rather than materialism arising as a
consequence of the neutral descriptive
formal basis of the framework what do
you think about that alex
yeah thanks
thanks daniel for articulating that so
well um
i think that's
uh basically right and just as a
specific example um
even if you even if you go so far as to
think that you can map this formula as
some formalism onto brain states
you don't have to think that brain
states get their
uh
status as desires or beliefs just from
their material constitution right you
could
if you believe that free will arises in
microtubules for example or something i
don't know how that works that theory by
the way i don't mean to disparage it
either i just i don't know how it works
but i'm using it as an example um maybe
you think that free will kind of somehow
bubbles up through this
uh free will at smaller scales or
something right so i just don't think
that even if we take this as a
description of the brain that we're
committed to
anything so heavy as materialism
thanks alex david
yeah i i appreciate your research i'm
not here to like debate uh dualism here
i just think that uh if we could
recognize what are the assumptions
or
axioms so you have questions
and that's why i like your focus on on
uh
motor control connected to sense
perception
so if there's uh your perception of a
unified eye
and even you know like daniel in his
research on ants or something like that
that uh okay there's you know david alex
uh
you know daniel all the panels to
ali and dean
uh that that are talking to each other
we might refer to ourselves as a name
but is there a unified eye
and you know so okay that's an axiom
that is based on a dualistic tradition
that may or may not be accurate and if
you say well there's a sum total
of forces that are limited through the
free energy principle that we refer to
as unified eye that makes decisions
but that's more a lexical misnomer and
even if you think daniel's uh research
and answer something like that that a
question like is there a unified ant
that avoids death that tries to survive
why does the ant
have some sort of will to live if i
argue that that's also non-materialistic
the ants
will to live or that there's a unified
force
so i mean you could have a materialistic
explanation like higher order rules and
just leave it that i believe that these
higher order rules stem from genetics or
some sort of uh
uh you know parallel what i call ant uh
reverse
anthropomorphization of machine learning
where an ant has some sort of will to
survive and therefore you know if you
try to step on an ant it's going to move
the other direction or something like
that but is there actually unified force
in the ant that is uh
telling it to survive that causes it to
act in a unified way or is it just uh
you know the free energy principle and a
reduction of all of the various uh sense
perceptions
and uh and and uh you know so we are
using these axioms from a dualistic
uh
perspective you know like specifically
or called the unified eye
uh that makes more sense as a
non-material force that chooses the eye
that's not my body chooses to make this
action
um and so if active inference is saying
no it's a sum total of sense perception
some sort of higher order rules that are
acquired through a combination of uh
genetics and
other
you know machine like processes
that uh
that we use the language description as
i
but uh you know the mathematics is
really saying that's not really accurate
and alex to you and i'll also just
recall
way back when
in 2222
when we discussed your paper
psychophysical identity and free energy
which very
directly tackles this question of
identity materialism physicalism various
other processes just want to drop that
note
and feel free to reply that
yeah that's great um yeah yeah the
reason i get so excited about this stuff
is that i i care about it and i
definitely
don't take like a sort of
default materialist position on this
stuff um
so i guess i mean overall david like my
my view here is sort of
about this self and uh you know the self
and the self with the capital s maybe in
some like you know buddhist type
traditions i'm actually a fairly
um
far on the on the mystical end of the
spectrum myself and and for that reason
i don't expect no i'm sorry this is
maybe not addressing what you said in
all its nuance but basically
the gist of how i see this is
you shouldn't expect that thing the
really special thing that we don't want
to eliminate you shouldn't expect it to
show up in our descriptions of things
because you can't describe it anyway
it's transcendent
so uh you know
even if the brain is identical with the
mind insofar as we can describe the mind
the mind isn't identical with the mind
and so far as we can describe the mind
right it's the it's the thing it's the
big self that we can't ever pin down
with words
um and actually out of respect for that
thing um
i am happy for not to show up in
the descriptions that we give of how
this how the material stuff works or
even how how anything works right
because insofar as you can reduce it to
a description it's not that thing
thanks alex and and to kind of add some
thoughts there um
the paper clearly delineates two
variants or applications of the active
inference formalism which is mai motor
active inference and dai decision active
inference and the the two theories
differ in
at least two important ways
uh or two two these two applications of
the frameworks differ in at least two
important ways the first is the
phenomena
that they are targeting to describe
whether discrete decision-making and
planning behavior or whether motor
behavior
and then there's the question of
discrete and continuous modeling and so
for reasons of biology and historical
precedent the motor models have come
from the continuous category
while many of the decision-making models
which often map onto things that are
legitimately categorical in the world
like a team maze
or a planning or sentence generation
task
has a discreteness or a categoricalness
to its basis
and
that made me think about linear
regression as i really like to think
about because
in the history of linear regressions no
one said you used a linear regression to
model the stimuli intensity and the
behavioral response so you think people
are a linear regression
and this is another mathematical
formalism
that in some ways although i'm happy to
also update my model on this
is
able to be interpreted but not the only
interpretation as having an equal
epistemic claim to the territory
as a linear model because they're
formalisms and the least squares error
in a linear aggression that which fits
which is not the only norm one could
choose but whatever function is used as
the imperative to fit that linear
regression
could be playing an analogous role to
like the calculation of variational free
energy it could be purely understood as
a modeling heuristic that's used to make
statistical comparisons
within a model
and then
also the linear regression framework can
be used to make discrete decisions like
break point regression where you can
contrast two different alternative
models and you can say
is it more consistent with one
regression or is it possible that
there's some break point a two parameter
model that we're going to identify and
so
i try to always be
thinking like we're on the freeway and
here's the action framework and here's
the linear regression framework and if
there's going to be some claim about
active inference or free energy
principle at all
about what the formalism means
i always like jumping from car to car
and thinking would people or do they or
have they said that about linear
aggression
and if they can't there better be a good
reason why they can't for example people
who are committed to taking an
interpretation
of the territory based upon anything of
the active
map do they think that that is something
that's true of all different statistical
modeling frameworks and they'd apply
that to a linear aggression
or is there something different in the
active inference formalisms that
legitimize or warrant that kind of a
interpretation beyond the linear
regression
that was the first point and then the
second point was about
alex very beautifully said with like not
expecting the transcendence
and that which cannot
um be named or however we want to think
about that space to appear in the
imminent and in the specific
realizations
i think it's very important that the
axioms are
stated
in
self-contained scientific argumentation
and rhetoric
although
unstated axioms come in at least two
types
one are the secret axioms that you made
and snuck in
like we didn't mention this issue but
we're going to use it as if it was an
axiom in in our deployment of a broader
argument later in section 9.
alternatively
an issue might not be addressed
because the argument is agnostic or
orthogonal or blanketed with respect to
that axiom
like you didn't mention what color shirt
you're wearing because
not you're going to use it
and slip it into the argument later but
rather that the argument being made is
uncorrelated or is not related to the
shirt color
so
i think that the
um potentially even aware
avoidance of the metaphysical
baggage
precursor
exploration in this paper
is not to say that the issues are
unimportant as various other work by all
the authors actually speaks to
but rather that this can be understood
as a specific sequence
of thoughts and rhetoric and symbols
that update belief
on the relatively narrow although still
quite broad question
of whether the concepts categories of b
d and i
can map to aspects of
the active framework just like the
linear regression slope could be mapped
on to the concept influence of x on y
not that that still wouldn't have some
ability to be critiqued in the future or
nuanced by future modeling but
you could just say the linear regression
model is not inconsistent does not
contradict
not that it proves but it does not
folk regressionology
so active inference models do not
contradict folk psychology
linear aggression models do not
contradict or negate folk causal
inference
anything that's going to break beyond
that epistemic map
is going to need to make a special case
beyond
people have interpreted this way or
somebody who wasn't paying attention
might make the mistake of believing x
so sorry for the extended piece there
but i think there's so many important
aspects that this paper like either
guides us on
and also takes us
to a vista of
dean
i'm not going to be able to articulate
it as clearly as you just did but here's
my thing so coming at the paper
with
my background my question ended up being
so if we're going to compare something
that adds two things up a belief
and a desire and out pops and an
intention
and then last week with alex on or with
sorry alex with ryan on here
we started moving to the idea that with
expected free energy
the the ability to see the discrete the
difference between the ambiguous
and the risk
was a difference so it's not an i'm not
an adding up
to come to some conclusion it was an
actual knowing
that
we want to try to move things that are
apart closer together and so
from the standpoint of writing the paper
now the question is
can those things
work
in concert and one approach which says
these things add up and then we behave
accordingly
work at the same time as this other way
of quantifying which says
there's a variational part that we're
trying to minimize and there's an
expected part that we're trying to
juggle as well
and so
i think
when you get to the closer to the end of
the paper and you talk about the world
to mind and the mind to world
that isn't necessarily always attitude
that's still a differential
but it i don't think
you
as as writers of this paper
disqualified what's going on with the
well
we can add these two things together and
that's what is what pops up all i think
and it said through paper many times is
under these particular types of sins
the difference
seems to
seems to also
determine what degree of desire or
belief
or ducks
i can't say doxacity
might pertain to that expected free a
free ener sorry expected free energy
difference
so again that's not as eloquent as
daniel or you can describe it but from
somebody who's way down here and just
trying to make sure that in my own head
that image right there that's up there
where suddenly the circumstances have
changed and i've gone to a desire that
says well i can't change gravity so i'm
going to make the biggest crater i
possibly can
instead of the outcome which i'd like
which is to continue to exist
maybe my entity my identity now is how
big a hole in here i can make
so that's a difference as opposed to an
adding up
thanks alex feel free to
respond and also
we'll look at expected free energy and
the simulation it'll be great to explore
those
yeah cool yeah so i think i got the
point about halfway through i'm i'm
seeing where you're getting it's
interesting so
i think
i mean the
the
first first my first answer was well um
okay if we we shouldn't think of belief
plus desire equals intention as
literally involving a sum
um you know since i've been doing a lot
of a lot of writing code lately is for
work and and i would think of it as like
well we define the sum operator for
belief and desire as just the thing that
active inference does right essentially
right basically belief plus desire means
take the chaotic divergence but a more
informative answer is
i mean if you want to think of it as a
mathematical type operation like a sum
or a difference i think you're right
being that it's much more like a
difference it's much more like intention
equals desire minus belief
right so it's like you have your model
of the worlds you see what the
difference is between the belief and the
and the
uh sorry between your model and
currently sorry you have your model of
what you want the world to be like
rather you see what the difference is
between that and your model of what the
world is like and uh and that gives you
the especially free energy but um i know
you said we get to this in a second
daniel but um i think you could pretty
much literally see this in the expected
free energy
um
in the kl term there right so yeah so
you could expand that so q of the
divergence between q and p you can you
can write this out in a way that's you
know where you're subtracting one uh
entropy from another basically and so
you can see it as literally a difference
so if you if you want to map it on to
the difference concept that's pretty
straightforward
and that's one feature of the logarithm
function
as a modeling heuristic not metaphysical
truth that
division
is a division of different terms like
the ratio
is related to the subtraction of the log
of the ratio so there's various reasons
why like log likelihoods are used and
it's also a core function that's
deployed in the kl divergence as well as
entropy
terms and then just
yes duvet but just to get through the
variables here
it's written out in the paper but a kl
divergence is
describing a divergence not a distance
between what are on the two sides of the
double line
and this is the q variational
distribution
of observations over a time horizon
conditioned upon policy
which serves also very important
function heuristically especially in the
discrete case
and the divergence between that
observations conditioned on policy
and
the
posterior distribution on observations
through time
so just that's what's in the kl term and
we explore this also more in the dot
zero and we can return to it as well but
just wanted to clarify like
and contextualize this to some of our
early discussions like this is the y
equals mx plus b
of this framework and the least squares
is like fitting the minimum of something
and so again to go beyond the
interpretation of linear modeling here
not that this is a linear model
requires sometimes describing this
either the specifics of this model and
how it differs or taking a vast or
potentially extremely untenable position
about the naive interpretation of
variables in arbitrary equations which i
think is fair to say is an untenable
position which puts the onus of people
making metaphysical interpretations or
claims about this line
into a place where the specifics of this
line
must be addressed
dean and then dave
just real quick i i think
for me it's it's hard to determine
whether or not
uh a relationship or a diversion or the
difference
is
material or not and so for me
sometimes that just depends sometimes i
can actually
see the edges of the relationship and
sometimes it's very very fluid and it's
hard to determine whether or not there's
something material about that and and
that's actually baked into this formula
too so
i don't know what others think about
that but i mean there is an aspect of
this that
is written in but i don't know if we can
actually
lock it down and say
that that thing that relationship there
is actually material or not
so
thanks dean david
yeah i think the
activity you know just looking at it as
a statistical model could be used
uh to model
any higher order rules with a feedback
mechanism whether the origins of them
are material or not so we don't have to
you know go in america around
uh talking about
what's the origin of these higher order
rules
um
and yeah i was just thinking the you
know the phenomena folk psychology
applying to humans and the belief desire
and tension model if we were looking at
a simpler model you know i think like
obviously you know daniel studied ants
uh but at what level is there
uh
sense perception
and motor control
and
does that need
um
a controller it was just a pure feedback
mechanism like action reaction
and their decision
is made based on higher order rules
that
you know i don't know if you'd consider
an ant if you you just simplify it like
uh
um
eat survive and even you know if an ant
doesn't have reproduce uh if even you
eliminate like an ant colony where only
the queen reproduces and and possibly in
humans you could say the only difference
between a human
and the ant is you add the reproduce but
you have these higher order rules of
basically um survive and you know maybe
that's maybe there's only one higher
order rule or maybe you want to give a
whole bunch of higher order rules
uh and then you define that in your
free energy principle like okay so you
have the sense perception
and then you have
the movement
and uh you know so how you define the
variables in the feedback mechanism
um you active inference uh mathematical
framework could model it no matter how
you
uh
define it and uh you know this thing
also mean obviously we're focusing on on
humans but it might be more simplified
to uh
focus on uh
you know the most simplified uh species
even plants maybe that they don't have a
survive instinct that they i mean they
have some sort of survive instinct but
like you know insect that could uh try
to survive if i try to squash an insect
it's going to move in order to try to
survive and it's a clear example of
sense perception the insect senses me
you know trying to trying to kill it god
forbid and then moves out of the way of
what exactly caused it and so you're
just going to hypothesize well of course
it has some sort of survival instinct
and the sensory perception feeds in to
uh its motor control movement versus if
it's just seeking food or like a maslow
hierarchy of needs
and uh you know i like the terminology
you know anthropo if we're
anthropomorphizing you know the ant
or are we reverse amphetamizing the
machine
that the fact is in terms of sense
perception motor control
we understand how the robot computer
works much better than the mind
and so are the active inference
equations really more suited to
machine learning uh robotic automation
and then where you reverse
anthropomorphizing that to uh
the human mind
but you know certainly the equations are
valuable
because you know largely they could be
interchanged and defined how you want
them to
thanks
i'll connect some um
ant
thoughts to the skydiver so dean has
returned to this example of the skydiver
as being like well if i can't change
gravity my policies whether mental
attention policies prey or no prey
um you know do this motor behavior or do
the speech behavior which is a motor
behavior as well
condition on policy i'm not going to be
able to influence gravity and
then once updates there prior that also
conditioned upon various action policies
they're not going to be able to open a
functional parachute
then there's this discrete shift as
you've described to like making the
biggest crater
and
hearing about the ants
over the years
it makes me think about folk biology
like the notion that people have in
terms of their received understanding
that there is like a
drive to survive or a drive to reproduce
or drive to do various numbers of things
it's almost like the bdi of evolutionary
biology or of ecology and i'm thinking
about the case where uh
a nest mate is out foraging for the
colony and then they're being like
messed with by somebody with like a
magnifying glass or being touching them
and at first it's like evading now that
behavior looks a lot like a solitary
insect that might be trying to evade and
survive ostensibly to reproduce and
increase like its
individual offspring if one is still
within the folk biological realm
and then it's like there's a switch
where the nest mate is actually like
no
the evolutionary unit is the colony and
so it goes for the biggest crater
possible and that's even embodied in the
anatomy of some insects for example with
a hooked stinger where they can't
they're committing six-legged death
to
compose a broader high fitness entity at
the colony scale and so that's like a
behavioral shift from trying to open the
individual nest mate
parachute to make the biggest crater on
the attacker possible for the good of
the colony
and that
no matter how hard you try to map that
to the behavior of a solitary insect
will be
along a potentially didactic or
interesting but ultimately facetious
route because the colony is the
evolutionary unit for these obligately
used social species
and so one will be scratching their head
at various of the behaviors and that's
why the value of a descriptive framework
is so important because we're able to
describe various computational qualities
and
not be inconsistent or contradicting
folk in its psychology
while also
remaining absolutely
impartial to questions of what ants
think for example
and so we can have computational
representations of ant decision making
and cognition perception cognition
action impact
and we can link it to natural language
descriptions through the active
inference ontology as well as through
potentially other ontologies like ant
folk psychology
and we can take that yes and
and other people can add other yes ands
if they want
but
they're gonna have to take a different
tack
to uncouple the relationship between
these computational quantities
and try to interject a wedge and say no
it does contradict folk psychology
that's a different argument then
that
relationship is in violating some other
third belief system that i'm bringing to
the table
so hope that um
addresses some of it and thanks blue for
your questions in the chat there
um ali
would you like to
raise anything or take us to
a question or area that you want to
focus on
uh yeah and one more thing about this
discussion is uh bringing uh
personal semiotics into table i think
well
active inference actually i believe is a
kind of
uh
iconic
symbol as opposed to
uh index because you see in person
semiotics
for index we need to necessarily
allow some kind of a causal relationship
between
the symbol and the index but
for
icons we only need to have some
isomorphic
isomorphic similarities i'm not not to
say similarity because the similarity is
a
very vague term some isomorphism between
the symbol and the icon so
ideally active inference is a kind of um
let's say structure preserving mapping
between the behavior and the model so uh
i guess if we
can if we could differentiate between
icons and indices
some of these at least
confusions could possibly could
potentially be
well resolved
so icons indices of process semiotics
thanks for sharing that and it connects
to some of the discussions we've had on
process ontologies
as well
alex
yeah just really quickly i mean i gotta
say i don't know that much about
processed semiotics but
that way of thinking of active inference
and of theories in general as like
iconic representations is pretty much
how i think of
theories and how i mean the most recent
thing i published with yaakov movie we
basically said um
that you can think of scientific
theories as relating to the world by a
process uh non-process a relation
of sort of structural similarity uh
isomorphous isomorphism being the sort
of illuminate case
um so i just i i agree with that and i
think it's
it kind of comes right back to a lot of
what we discussed like i i i'm as i get
older i start to think that maybe
there's something to the essential
indexical idea that like i has a special
role to play
you know the letter capital i in english
but um other than that i think things
pretty much function
descriptively and uh and i think
description functions
via isomorphism or similarities so i
totally agree
awesome
that reminds me of um the book anthem by
rand
where the word i is not included in the
linguistics and then the end of the book
not you know spoiler alert um that word
i is rediscovered
and so it's kind of an allegory that
traces some of these questions about the
potentially special role
of the bodily identity
but it's very interesting that these
frameworks actually are
engaging
or
with this augmented perspective for
example that ali has raised
that these theories can be seen as
already having been engaged in
a discourse that people might not expect
like predictive processing is what the
brain is doing do you agree or deny
what's the evidence for predictive
processing being active in the brain
versus not active in the brain is this
neural signal recording that we made
more consistent with a predictive or
non-predictive model
it takes that miso range of what the
system is doing
and it partitions it as we heard also
from ryan
previously into like well predictive
processing can't be
invalidated
not nor can linear regression framework
nor can active inference framework
any specific model
is now engaged in a specific model
evidence comparison and then one can
choose what kind of model comparisons
they want to make
knowing that they're not going to be
able to exhaustively consider all
possible cognitive architectures
but
also
any invalidation or relative model fit
or adequacy amongst different models at
this specific
level
are speaking
only rhetorically
to the truth or the validity or the
adequacy of the higher level
inviolable framework
there's a lot there to explore do it
yeah maybe we could tie this back to the
eliminativism
um
and uh you know the anthropomorphisms if
you know you ascribe an eye to the
computer you say that's a logical
fallacy of anthropomorphism because
there is no i it's just following code
or even to uh the ant if uh
you know mammals may be uh but but you
know insects communicate different sense
pheromones and you want to
anthropomorphize an eye to the ant that
like the the ant is saying i
want to communicate with my fellow aunts
for a purpose and it's like no no that's
not that's an anthropomorphism logical
fallacy the ant is just uh following
genetic code
and then you say well uh
really for humans also that you know
we're morphizing uh the mind and that
there is no i
related to uh unified eye related to the
me that even right now that you know i
am communicating with uh with you you
find gentlemen
but that's a misnomer
and in terms that it's just uh
me following uh my my predictive coding
and that uh you know just for the
purpose of language
i'm referring it to is i talking to you
but you know that's just like a computer
sending code to another computer or an
aunt sending pheromones or whatever
method of communication it uses and
that's just the language and lexicon
that we use
yeah
it's uh
it's a dialogue that has played out in
not only girdle escher bach but many
college dorm rooms many late night
sessions
one participant or perspective believes
that they have for example the ability
to choose and have agency and the other
disregards that position or one believes
that there's something and there's a
divergence in their perspective
i think this is just the heart of the
map territory debate in the distributed
cognitive setting
as all cognitive systems ultimately are
even what is called individual behavior
is just referring to collective behavior
at another scale
for example one person can say this
conversation can be modeled using active
inference or this conversation can be
modeled using predictive processing just
like it could be constructed with a
linear regression or family of linear
regressions and somebody else could say
this conversation is
nothing but
linear aggressions nothing but
predictive processing nothing but active
inference
someone might believe that and if they
believe that it would be true that that
is their perspective
i don't know if that would make it true
but
they would be taking they would be
stepping into a territory that the
person who remains with both feet in
instrumentalism i'm choosing to model it
this way or i'm
testing a portfolio of different models
around how we could model our difference
in perspective
maybe one can say that they have uh been
too timid and they haven't actually
engaged in the real question which is
what's really happening not with how
you're modeling it
but that's a whole another debate
alex and then do it
yeah um
i just think i mean this this might tie
into the stuff in section nine that
maybe we'll get to we don't have to jump
to i'm just saying uh
uh basically i
i agree you could raise these questions
for any of these systems people machines
ants uh
protons whatever and uh
and i think there's an argument to be
made that there's not a clear place to
draw the line there but it could go
either way with respect to all of those
right i i think that you know
you could be antimorphizing in all of
those cases or none of them
it's not easy to
i don't think it's easy to draw a line
somewhere along the sort of
evolutionary continuum or anything like
that to say although there's an argument
about temporal depth of generative
models that's interesting that
touched on a couple of papers here and
there but um
you know i think
uh
the the cool thing about
uh active inference and the free energy
principle stuff is that it applies
across scales
um so i think that to me that means that
you're faced with a similar problem
um at whatever scale you consider it um
i just gotta throw out there i probably
gonna have to leave around 12 30 eastern
so i'll say that now so that i can just
abruptly
uh close my window
so we're in the summary of main argument
section nine
so
alex what is the main argument and also
in the contexts and audiences that
you've presented it in how do you feel
like it lands or what cognitive updates
are you aiming to achieve with this
argument as constructed and communicated
is this section nine i think actually
may have been section eight but um sorry
okay section eight desire is an
affective statement
i meant ten
okay um i i don't want to totally bypass
your question i just think nine is kind
of a summary of the argument thus far so
all right
how about ten let's talk about direction
of fit
yeah so i mean so the
sorry the
sort of the point here was just that
there's a this
certainly is relevant to a lot of what
we're discussing there's a
straightforward way to generalize this
beyond systems that you would
necessarily intuitively describe as
having beliefs and desires
and we can just talk about any system
that's described by active inference
by this framework or that's describable
accurately by this framework you can
talk about the difference between q and
p
and this i think also ties into
some of the work that maxwell ramstad
has done on
um just the idea that you know uh
the generative model is sort of
representation or it's sort of a
representation embodied by the system if
it's a representation we still disagree
about that anyway the generative model
and the
approximate recognition model are sort
of always there even if you apply these
frameworks um to describe very simple
systems and you can you can see
something desire-like or belief-like in
those
and we just remained very neutral on on
that
in this paper on the question whether
there really are beliefs and desires in
these sort of
extended cases by extended i mean
not necessarily paradigmatic right so if
if beliefs and desires paradigmatically
apply to like people
and then maybe to ants and i would say
definitely dogs you know um
then uh this this stuff in section 10 is
is about what you can say without
necessarily committing to beliefs and
desires and those in the in the edge
cases
um but you can still say that there's at
least an ingredient of beliefs and
desires which is a direction of fit
um
that's
sums it up
so how could this be used in one case
for a human entity in the folk
psychological way
and in another case for some entity that
people would maybe say
that type of folk psychology would be
inadmissible for
um
i mean as far as how it could be used in
the case of
of people that have beliefs and desires
or that we think do i think it's pretty
it's pretty straightforward right it's
just saying well any kind of folks like
a long physical explanation you can give
of a person's behavior you can
it's consistent with the description of
that person in terms of active inference
um
i guess then the only question is like
in in case of a system that might be
not clearly
that you wouldn't necessarily think of
as having a psychology in the same sense
uh what kinds of things would you want
to say about it um
i think
i think there's an example that made
into a paper about like a a plant
reaching towards the light or something
or it's sort of these simple
simpler sort of feedback systems right
where something there's like a set point
uh and the thing is approaching the set
point um
you can still think of the
of the prior distribution as having a uh
world to mind direction fit
right because it's it's the piece of the
system that brings it about that
um
that things change so that that
distribution
describes
uh you know reality
um
yeah so
uh
yeah and so you still have those so so
that's one example um
i don't know maybe like a bacterium
following some kind of
nutrient gradient or something i don't
really know about that stuff but
that's another example that might you
could you could describe directions of
fit to that creature and
i don't okay last last my last thought
on this i don't know why it would be
useful to do that necessarily uh i don't
know there might be reasons in
studying these systems that you want to
but if you did want to do it you could
understand it from the framework
just some brief thoughts and then ali so
first there's a paper of calvo and frist
in 2017 which is specifically applying
predictive processing and active to the
um vegetative case
and i think from the perspective of
behavioral analysis there's also
precedence
in the 1989 paper framework for plant
behavior by silvertown and gordon
so suffice to say that plants are
included within this cognitivist
modeling perspective and then it made me
think about how the surprise the
self-information
is an energy function it's what dampens
the spring and so maybe could you say
like the heavier ball with folk
ball psychology the heavier ball wants
to drop faster or it wants to make a
bigger crater or all these other things
just
again it doesn't have the agency to want
otherwise
given the initial conditions and the
rules of physics in that situation but
it's exactly like a person wanting to
make a small hole in the paper or
wanting to make a big hole and then
realizing that intention would be
analogous to an energy functional being
reduced by some kind of
purely physical system which does again
hint towards some of the potentially
non-materialist
implications legacy that do slip in
to
different
in cultured conversations around mind
um
yes alex any last thoughts on that just
real quick get on the ball example i
mean
i think there is a sense of course in
which this framework applies but i think
if anything the ball wouldn't
have a desire or
if the system involving the bomb line
though right so because the
the term that would that would pull the
ball towards the ground or whatever
wouldn't really be in the makeup of the
ball
but and so whether that larger system
has a proto belief or desire i don't
know
ali and again alex you feel free to
depart whenever but ollie go for it
uh well yeah i'm not sure if we have
enough time to get into this question
i mean if not we can uh discuss it in
the dark too but
i had a question about
the aesthetic experience and the
pleasure or
positive valence we get from engaging
with works of art uh in particular i'm
talking about unexpected plot twists in
movies or novels or different kinds of
intentional ambiguities and some
artworks
for instance the works of m.c escher and
his impossible geometries
will immediately come to mind
and the sense of excitement and joy they
tend to induce in the audience
in fact playing around with these kinds
of
defamiliarizations as literary critics
like to call them seems to be more of a
rule than an exception in any creative
endeavor on the other hand outside the
safety of the world of arts
we generally don't like to be
encountered with too much unexpectedness
as we've seen
so i wonder whether or how
these kinds of aesthetic reactions can
be integrated
within the formalism of active inference
are they special cases of information
seeking drives or there's a whole other
story going on here
go for this and then
thanks again for your time here yeah
yeah yeah i'll check out after this
thank you so much i love these
discussions i knew it would be an
interesting interesting crowd
interesting uh topics
um i gotta say i i don't know much about
what you just asked about um ellie but i
love this this topic um i'm i'm coming i
actually come from a background of
aesthetics as well i should say but
anyway i know there's a lot of work on
this so i know that predictive process
under the banner of predictive
processing there's a whole lot of work
in aesthetics these days on i think
suggesting a lot of something very
similar to what you're saying that
there's clearly a relationship here
between surprisal and unexpectedness and
predictions and
the joy that we get out of and other
emotions that we get out of artworks and
i i would love to to know more about
this i haven't had time to look into it
but i i think daniel's put a uh
this was a uh uh also a predictive
processing type paper with a incredible
title
move me astonish me delight my eyes and
brain and then enter the subtitle
sequel
title um perhaps in the dot 2 let's
sketch this out let's act let's look at
the formalisms and let's do some
mappings so someone said i believe that
mondrian is an amazing painter and i
want to go to a space where i do see
beautiful art and i want to have this
kind of experience or something like
that but let's explore that in the dot 2
with some of the bdis and the aesthetics
of uncultured experiences
yeah sure if i could just
just really quickly i think that the
challenge there is going to be
that sometimes prediction error is fine
and sometimes it's not we need to figure
out right there's probably some
complicated way of saying
what the difference is between those
cases but that's that's as far as my
intuition goes yeah i'd love to discuss
it
um
thanks again see you later thank you all
bye bye
great dean
yeah i just wanted to kind of jump on
that point that wally was making i
i think that
in the in this in the
i just want to make sure i got the right
section of the paper here
uh sorry the free energy principle and
the direction of fit yeah
sort of to tag on what ali and and alex
were saying there's a there's a
statement here that says
holding the value of the observation
constantly in this equation
f decreases as the approximate posterior
distribution q of the state approaches
the posterior
the q s term therefore is
forwardly belief-like mind-to-world
direction of fit in that its value
changes to accommodate
new observations i think that the usher
and the mondrian and every time i go to
a
a sporting event
my openness my accommodation
to
what is perceived as an uncertain
outcome is the thing that draws my
attention
and i think daniel's point of let's
let's map that out let's see how long
some people are able to hold that
ambiguity
space
and not necessarily see it as a risk
is
both immaterial until it materializes
and
is a process that i think a lot of
people want to go through
because there's there's something to
that
isn't just attention
in from it isn't just information
seeking but it may also satiate certain
desires so i think that is a point to
mapping that we should
maybe spend a little bit of time on
because i don't know that when you open
a space up for something to eventually
happen
you're you're
imposing what the final material
form should take you're simply leaving
something open in the hopes that
something interesting
i.e
an escher painting might end up being in
the next room i mean this is what
happens when i
go to museums in spain it's i'm not
looking to find
the particular
daly
i'm looking to go into that space and be
surprised
so i wonder how that actually does map
out using these formalisms
yes it reminds me of when in the dot
zero ryan described like the different
reasons and the different nuancing the
types of information seeking
that's very relevant i'm navigating
through this museum to reduce my
uncertainty about where that one piece
that i came to see is
the target driven epistemic foraging
from a more general like i don't know
what is in that other room
that is going to influence my
probability of moving room to room and
certainly with the eye cicading
that is how we maintain a visual field
that appears to have roughly equal
resolution
via our generative model of vision and
ocular motor cicading to regions of
maximal information
distinctly uncoupled from only what
regions are most rewarding though
people's gaze does tend to linger in
certain regions that might be perceived
as rewarding
that isn't the only imperative
and that's why it's so special and
relevant
to have a
cross system and multi-scale behavioral
modeling framework like active inference
that helps us understand the pure
static field eyes trying to latch on to
anything mode
from the
gaze
on a candle flame during meditation or
one region of particular beauty in
another visual scene dean
yeah just real quick and i think that
also
ali thank you you raised sembiotics and
i'm a pierce fan so
there's a there's a huge piece of that
involved in this as well as so what is
the signal
that that very much there's that there's
a slide in here that we didn't get to
but when the ice cream cone is looking
off into the distance at that
at that ice cream truck
where do we where do we place that in
the foreground or in the background and
that is a huge i think that plays a huge
part in
in their
the role of the third person now looking
at the the observer looking at the
observer and getting that sort of
recursive aspect involved in this as
well so
again i don't know how that we will have
to
we'll borrow daniels
how to be able to map that as a nine one
or as a three seven and then maybe put
it on a likert scale because i think all
of that kind of is a potential way for
this to sort of make a sense i wasn't
bringing up with alex the idea that
like literally beliefs and desires add
up to intentions i was sort of saying
that tongue-in-cheek just to be able to
show the difference when something is
discreet
and and how we try to bring them
together
and this observer of an observer thing
um although it's not i don't think it's
alex's and and the other two authors
primary goal here
but i but i do think they lower the bar
in terms of bringing
some of the more folk out spoke aspects
of this into the formalism aspects
yes and it was a very clever and
interesting response which is it depends
on what is meant by addition what does
it mean for um
dean bless ali does that mean they're
both going to stand on a scale and we're
measuring their mass
does it mean that we're going to stack
them head to toe and then consider the
length does it mean that they're going
to interact in a certain context
does it mean we're going to blend them
up i mean there isn't an intrinsic
definition to what the addition operator
or any operator means in a formal system
and so it opens up the idea that we
could have whether specific symbols or
just here's how we're using this symbol
here
and use that to refer to relatively
potentially complex and multi-step
operations
or operations that can be phrased in
multi-step
for example a multiplication on the
processor might happen in a different
way than somebody is cognitively
thinking about it but that
is um
as the title hints
not contradictory
not that one validates or encompasses or
proves the other but there's so many
things that are not contradictory an
active inference may be contradictory of
certain things
let's make a list what is active
inference contradictory of what is folk
psychology contradicting of and we can
make all of that mapping in the right
knowledge management system
and the claim of the article as i guess
ryan's
imperative was was to make this claim
that as they've operationalized both
active inference models do not
contradict folk psychology and that's
quite an interesting claim
yeah just real quick i i think daniel
the point is
i'm rephrasing it in my own
from my own view which is you raise a
lot of different joint probabilities
that
by their nature are arbitrary and i
think that's important to keep in mind
this leaves open
the possibility of looking at things a
variety of different ways
yeah and just to speak to the joint
probability density so the joint
probability density in the bayesian
modeling approach is like where there's
a comma so instead of a conditioned on b
it's like the joint distribution of a
and b
right
y
a and b why not b and y
why not these three
and so
there's always
something like a periphery that the
model comes from
and we can be blanketed off from it and
that actually serves as a scientific and
really meta-scientific
way
to have rigor and accessibility
potentially of the models to respect
when we're in the regime of attention of
a model what kinds of claims can or
cannot be supported what kinds of
contradictions are or not tenable to
make
and then also have the yes and with
respecting that that joint distribution
was not
handed down from on high it is not the
only possible joint distribution that
could have been selected
and so we can separate off how did these
real researchers in this real situation
come to focus on that phenomena and pick
this joint distribution
from
conditioned on the joint distribution
what was the actual conversation and
consequences and modeling they performed
david
yeah it's all fascinating um
i guess i had
two separate points i wanted to express
and they might be more general because
it's my first time on the stream than
uh uh it's related to this paper but
specific to active inference in general
and the interdisciplinary studies um
what my streaming partner uh jennifer
scharf calls herself church of entropy
we've been three years now uh talking
about consciousness and i showed her the
free energy principle and she
immediately
said that uh isn't that just the least
action principle
and uh
i mean it's not directly related to this
paper but i could see that in terms of
uh
um
you know my second point i'll call gold
directed behavior in general
and uh you know if you want to say that
there's only one motivating force
in
active inference and that's the
free energy principle which is basically
a restating of
the least action principle
and then at a second point uh
i went you know last week in metro
detroit they had the international
automation conference
and uh they had the latest in robotic
arms and technology
for uh manufacture and they had on
display um
you know a lot of what we'll call sense
perception and motor control
specifically robotic arms that
don't just repeat the same action or
even have like a sensor embedded when
but have an embedded sensor of a camera
that will recognize the object and then
create a set of rules in order to uh
tell the robotic arm the best uh
trajectory in order to pick up the
object and then in terms of uh like
old-school manufacturer where it would
just been taking an object and setting
it in one place where it actually has
some level of machine
learning intelligence where it could uh
intelligently design where to put the
object in terms of like stacking boxes
where it could uh you know the algorithm
of the computer could
determine
what's the best way to stack the objects
and then control the robotic arm to uh
to do that if it's like so for humans uh
just on the pure level of sense
perception
has goal-directed behavior how do i you
know if we have 100 million
uh cones and rods in her eye how do we
direct uh
our physical
capabilities of sense perception to
perceive the environment uh and saying
that could be modeled by these equations
and uh we'll call you know the free
energy principle least action principle
and then the decision making that uh uh
you know the goal uh directed behavior
like the like the automation computer it
has to have a goal code in order to act
and so it could action reaction sense
perception
uh
feedback mechanism in order to action
and then the equation are describing
gold-directed behavior and that's why
i'm a fan of the active inference model
because uh
as a dualist i mean as a scientist i
could let's describe these in purely
materialistic things and we don't have
to get too much into the theology or
uh you know what's the origin of these
higher order rules even if you want to
assume that all higher order rules are
material in uh in origin
but i think the equations in general
could model it no matter what their
origin is and it's a you know just a
good framework to understand uh
um
you know all these theories the goal
directed behavior at all aspects and
then to put on you know the last spin on
it like the maslow's hierarchy of needs
in uh in like you know what is belief
desire
and uh you know that i would have
introspection or education that would
give me
um you know morals ethics that okay like
my body uh like i put the pithy and the
the expression i see the heart desires
the mind plots and the limb carry out
that uh that
i have the capability that my eyes see
my heart desires but my mind stops me
and says that's wrong
and uh even though
my sense perception saw it and my
desires told me that i should do it
somehow there's this higher order
principle of the mind that tells me
that's wrong and i'm not going to do it
and there's that control factor before
the limbs carry out
thank you i'll just make some short
points and then we can just close off
with what we're excited to explore in
the dot 2.
i really just appreciate what a lot of
people shared and i think
over these
discussions and the years
we're finding some clarities
around where are different
implications and consequences
what is entering into active inference
as a field and a filter and what is
coming out of it what's happening on the
playground and so there's just a lot to
explore then um livestream 45 just in
the last few weeks
and not to rehearse outside of this
paper regime of attention but the free
energy principle as it's rehearsed in
that paper
is establishing the particular partition
that's
markov blanketing off the figure from
the ground the thing which is able to
undergo repeated measurements in the
quantum sense from the thing that is not
that thing that's the particular
partition with the sensory active
internal external partition the
autonomous states the blanket states
from sparse coupling
unpacking the implications in terms of
bayesian inference in other words seeing
the flow
of those states as doing something that
is slash can be modeled as bayesian
inference and then finally understanding
paths in terms of a principle of least
action which has been starting to be
explored from at least the early path
formalizations of active inference years
ago
and i think in the last
two weeks to two years
taking a new view on that
through a lot of the work on geometry
and analysis by dalton maxwell and other
collaborators so indeed this path
formalization is very relevant and the
principle of least action which isn't
the principle of least motion it's not
the laziest thing it's not the one that
always works it's none of those things
but it's a framework for analyzing
behavior
and with that
what would people be excited to explore
next week or what would be something
that they didn't
have uncertainty or motivational drive
to explore before today but it has come
onto their horizon through this
discussion
yes ali then dean dude
uh well it was uh it was a really
fascinating discussion and uh
i thank you all for bringing such
interesting
interesting topics
um
onto the table but um i'm very much
looking forward to that too and uh
i also had a couple of questions i'm
interested in exploring uh the
phenomenological aspects of folk
psychology especially
belief and desire
and also
the relation of dai to
abnormal psychology which is
just briefly touched on in the paper but
uh not
in detail and uh
yeah i hope uh the next session
uh will be at least as fascinating as
this one
thank you ali dean
i already said what i'm hoping we can
look at in this point too but i'll just
add this i think it's really interesting
that the term active inference
um i'll just say in in this calendar
year alone we've had a couple of papers
that have started typing active
inference we've had
outside the skull or extended active
inference and now we've got this dai and
mai and i think there's probably going
to be more
and so depending on how many authors are
available next week i might be asking
them a little bit about that too like is
that does that seem like
a natural roll out when you have these
scale-free ideas that you need these
these scale-friendly qualifiers just so
that it continues to make sense
thank you do it and then i'll make a
point on that dean
yeah and because this is my first uh
time site a lot of general stuff on
active inference in general and i try to
stick straight
to this paper um i think it'd be
interesting to cover more i asked the
question you know has active inference
even explained one qualia
and uh you know that uh
you know there's actually a model here
in in the equations could we describe
a single process a single
sense perception to decision making
and uh you know so like the human model
to uh um
a simpler life form or even say that uh
is in essence the you know the
automation like the machine learning
algorithms
uh for robotic arms
um is that in essence using these same
active
inference
computers i spoke to you know brac
online who i guess is an entrepreneur
thinking like real estate
uh but uh is is it
yeah what would the application of this
be uh
to uh
you know autonomous cars are more
complicated but like something the most
simplified version which is probably uh
robotic sensors and controlled movement
based on machine learning that uh and uh
and then
you know i said could we
try to explain
a single qualia in terms of what happens
when
i sent something
and
make some sort of movement
and then i was talking what would all of
the axioms uh necessary to in terms of
the
higher order rules or goal-oriented
behavior if they're not beliefs desires
intentions what are they and how are
they modeled into the equation what
happens when i perceive something and
that's translated into action uh what
axioms do we have to put into the model
to make it work as opposed to uh or in
comparison to the robotic arm that's
coded for that does that
thank you to all those returning and
first time and our second applied active
inference symposium which is going to be
in july 2022 is on robotics so we can
absolutely address a lot of the
applications
and also
adjacencies
and the the sense that i got maybe just
thinking of that robotic case is like a
little wind-up toy on a table we want to
build it
and
this discussion
because of how it is constituted and
enacted is helping us understand not
just all of the implications that go
into that wind-up toy but exploring a
lot of the consequences of the wind-up
toy and then there's people saying but
wasn't the table constructed and
wouldn't a different table have resulted
in a different wind-up toy behavior and
who placed it on the table and why are
tables designed that way and isn't table
just like a functional consequence of
anything being put on it and what are we
doing here how did we decide on that how
should we decide the next wind-up toy
and it just takes it in so many amazing
places so thanks to everybody in the
chat and joining live and of course to
the authors for the paper
see you in 46.2
thank you chance
bye
you